<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Italy | Roberto Aloi]]></title>
  <link href="http://prof3ta.github.com/blog/categories/italy/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://prof3ta.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-11-12T10:49:53+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://prof3ta.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Roberto Aloi]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[History of a Generation]]></title>
    <link href="http://prof3ta.github.com/blog/2012/09/12/history-of-a-generation/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-12T18:36:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://prof3ta.github.com/blog/2012/09/12/history-of-a-generation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I wanted to translate <a href="http://torto45.wordpress.com/2010/10/29/hello-world/" target="_blank">this blog post</a> into English, cause I believe it renders an almost perfect picture of Italy as it is today. This is a free translation and all the rights for the original blog post belong to the original author.</p>

<p>When I was a child, I was told:</p>

<blockquote><p>"Study, or you’ll go nowhere."</p></blockquote>

<p>So I’ve studied.</p>

<p>After completing my academic career, I’ve been told:</p>

<blockquote><p>"Why did you spend so much time on a degree? Don’t you know that’s a useless piece of paper? You’d better to learn a trade."</p></blockquote>

<p>I’ve learned a trade. Then, I’ve been told:</p>

<blockquote><p>"What a shame. You’ve studied so many years for that trade?”</p></blockquote>

<p>I moved ahead, and I left my job. I became penniless.</p>

<p><em>One day I was too young and inexperienced. The day after I was too old, with too much experience and too many titles.</em></p>

<p>I finally found a job. Well, not a permanent one. A temporary one, with no paid leave, no insurance, no pension, no bonuses, no severance, no rights. And I had to fight hard to keep that not-a-job. I decided not to have children, because of some sense of responsibility, and I grew up. Then I’ve been told, <a href="http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-1289005/Rise-bamboccioni-big-babies--Why-young-Italians-choosing-live-home.html" target="_blank">by someone who got his job in the 60s, when it was easy to get a job, despite of your education level</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>“You are a fool, a dupe who didn’t want to grow up and raise a family".</p></blockquote>

<p>In the meantime, I was paying his very own pension, saying a final goodbye to mine. Tired and grown up, I decided to have a baby. I’ve been told that:</p>

<blockquote><p>“Only an irresponsible person would have a child without a proper job and without a good economical background”.</p></blockquote>

<p>Given that I could not kill my son, I decided to emigrate. I went somewhere else. I found a safe place, and a good job. I was feeling good. I was feeling home. But one day, when the Italian system went bankrupt, I’ve then been told:</p>

<blockquote><p>“Why the hell did you flee? Why didn’t you help your Country?”.</p></blockquote>

<p>At that point, There was only one very reply:</p>

<blockquote><p>“Fuck off!”.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
