<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: emacs | Roberto Aloi]]></title>
  <link href="http://roberto-aloi.com/blog/categories/emacs/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://roberto-aloi.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-12-01T16:43:51+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://roberto-aloi.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Roberto Aloi]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Emacs Tips and Tricks]]></title>
    <link href="http://roberto-aloi.com/blog/2009/02/19/emacs-tips-and-tricks/"/>
    <updated>2009-02-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://roberto-aloi.com/blog/2009/02/19/emacs-tips-and-tricks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this blog post I collect some miscellaneous Emacs tips and tricks.</p>

<h2>Playing with Macros</h2>


<p>In Emacs, you can <em>record</em> a set of actions that you can then apply to a selected region. As an example, let's transform the following three lines:</p>

<pre>
First Line
Second Line
Third Line
</pre>


<p>into a list of items, using a macro:</p>

<pre>
- First Line
- Second Line
- Third Line
</pre>


<p>Put your cursor on the <code>First line</code>, then start recording a new keyboard macro by typing:</p>

<pre>C-x (</pre>


<p>Jump to the beginning of the line (<code>C-a</code>), insert a dash followed by a space (<code>- </code>) and then move your cursor down one line, so it resides on the <code>Second Line</code>.</p>

<p>Stop recording the macro:</p>

<pre>C-x )</pre>


<p>Now select the lines <code>Second Line</code> and <code>Third Line</code> and apply the newly recorded macro to the selected region by pressing:</p>

<pre>C-x C-k r</pre>


<p>You should now see the desired output.</p>

<h2>Swapping Words</h2>


<p>Say that you want to reverse the order of the parameter for the following function:</p>

<pre>
foo(Second, First) -&gt;
    ok.
</pre>


<p>Position the cursor between the words <code>Second</code> and <code>First</code>. Then, press:</p>

<pre>M-t</pre>


<p>You should obtain the following:</p>

<pre>
foo(First, Second) -&gt;
    ok.
</pre>




<h2>Swapping Lines</h2>


<p>Given the following two lines:</p>

<pre>
Second Line
First Line
</pre>


<p>Put the cursor at the beginning of <code>First Line</code> and press:</p>

<pre>C-x C-t</pre>


<p>You should get:</p>

<pre>
First Line
Second Line
</pre>




<h2>Version Control</h2>


<p>Emacs has support for the most common Version Control systems (e.g. <em>SVN</em>).</p>

<p>To check-in a single file directly from Emacs, simply follow the steps below:</p>

<ul>
<li>Press <code>C-x v v</code></li>
<li>Write a meaningful <em>change comment</em></li>
<li>Press <code>C-c C-c</code></li>
</ul>


<p>To revert changes for the current buffer:</p>

<p><code>C-x v u</code></p>

<p>To see the differences for a buffer before committing it:</p>

<p><code>C-x v =</code></p>

<h2>Executing a Shell Command</h2>


<p>If you want to execute a shell command within Emacs, you can simply type:</p>

<pre>M-!</pre>


<p>If you want to include the output into the current buffer, then:</p>

<pre>C-u M-!</pre>




<h2>Clipboard History</h2>


<p>Emacs keeps a clipboard history, allowing you to paste old clipboard entries. To utilize this function:</p>

<p>Press the following to paste:</p>

<pre>C-y</pre>


<p>And then browse the clipboard history by repeatedly typing:</p>

<pre>M-y</pre>




<h2>Create a Numbered List</h2>


<p>Say that you have a list of items that you want to convert into a numbered list:</p>

<pre>
first
second
third
</pre>




<pre>
1. first
2. second
3. third
</pre>


<p>There are many ways to achieve this. One is to use <a
href="http://www.gnu.org/software/emacs/manual/html_node/emacs/Keyboard-Macro-Counter.html#Keyboard-Macro-Counter"
target="_blank">the Emacs Keyboard Macro Counter</a>.</p>

<p>Position the cursor one line <em>above</em> your list and start registering a new macro:</p>

<pre>C-x (</pre>


<p>Insert a new counter value:</p>

<pre>C-x C-k C-i.</pre>


<p>A <code>0</code> will appear. Append a dot and a space:</p>

<pre>. </pre>


<p>Move the cursor to the next line and stop registering the macro:</p>

<pre>C-x )</pre>


<p>Select the list of items and apply the macro to the selected region:</p>

<pre>C-x C-k r</pre>


<p>Delete the <code>0</code> that you added at the beginning of the list and enjoy your brand new numbered list.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
